So I wanted to talk about um
the phenomenon of attraction
you know the beautiful object in the
world. Why are we attracted
to that which is beautiful?
>> Mhm.
And I thought about an uh I came up with
an analogy.
And so imagine well I'm sure many people
experience this when you uh go into a
toilet. You know I would like visit a
friend's house and you go into a toilet
after someone has used it and they've
sprayed some air freshener.
>> Mhm.
you know why they sprayed it and it
highlights that fact. You know, so no matter what
that fact. You know, so no matter what
lavender smell is there
>> for you, you know the underlying smell
of feces.
>> You you can't kind of ignore it. Well,
you can you can try obviously, but it's
like the person who who sprayed it
kind of can more easily ignore that
underlying smell.
>> It's like they focus on that
>> those fragrances and then they move on.
>> But the next person that comes in, he
you kind of know the context of that
spray. >> So, and it highlights that smell
>> So, and it highlights that smell
underneath.
>> Yeah.
And you can't and then the lavender
smell is not the same anymore.
>> Yeah. You start associating. [laughter]
>> Yes. You have to buy a different air
freshener and uh and so on. So
to I think that highlights the fact that
uh
you know any beautiful object
is only
why why why are we attracted to a
beautiful thing?
>> What makes it so valuable?
And I thought that it's its its value
is that it cover tries to at least or it
does cover up something a bad smell.
It covers up a the larger context of I'm
suffering here.
So I chase something pleasant. I go
after the beautiful because it helps me
uh ignore the the pain that I'm going
through. >> Helps you escape from it. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Helps you escape from it. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
Well, yeah. I think that's the the did
say that suda
put does [clears throat] not know any
other escape from an arisen unpleasant
feeling other than sensuality.
So that's why that's why it's like not
it's not as optional as many people
might think. It's like you know I could
give this up. Um I'm not necessarily
attached to the the
the sense pleasures and stuff because it
feels like yeah I can go without things
and so on and that's only true up to
certain extent because yes there is the
kind of a preferential add-on to the
whole experience of sensuality you know
like a proliferation of preferences and
so on but that's all driven by an
underlying existential need to go in
that direction because if you don't
there is this underlying uh pressure of
dooka that you that you're confined with
that you don't know escape from. So
that's why often a mere idea of giving
up sensuality
is frightening to people because that's
when you realize if you start toying
with the idea that's when you realize
how um how nonoptional it really is your
dependence on sensuality. It's like a
need. you know, you might have options
developed on top of that need, but
fundamentally it's a need because it's
the only form of escape that you know.
So um it's like for the for the same
reason basically people would then um
generally speaking it's like um
well they would try to find a way around
it to not have to do it because the just
the thought of not having an escape from
suffering the only one that you know now
leaves you really like with a
with an acute kind of recognition of
that as I said confinement cuz oh the
only means of escaping that I knew I was
told they don't work now what I'm left
with is like a complete confinement with
with my own existence duka and so on
that that well I don't know what to do
with that and it's kind of can be quite
trapping for the mind and scary that's
why whenever the Buddha was teaching lay
people um you know they stumbled upon
him and conversations
um he would give them like a progressive
talk in other words he'll be guiding
their mind rightly
um towards you know seeing the dam and
so on but it will always start with
first uplifting it
because what's about to follow it's going to
what's about to follow it's going to
crush it.
>> Yeah.
>> So if it's uplifted slightly higher then
when it's kind of brought down it won't
be like way too depressed so to speak it
will be right at the right level.
Obviously the Buddha could do that. I
mean all of the sutas explicitly say
that the lord saw that their mind is
ready and then he told them at the right
time to the right extent guiding their
mind and people can kind of gloss over
that sometimes it's like not a big deal
but it's a huge deal like the fact that
without a Buddhist guidance you need to
meet all those prerequisites and
requirements just to be maybe have a
possibility to see the signs of your
mind that's how deeply people do not see
their mind for themselves.
So you need to be like fully withdrawn
from sensuality. Um then it says like
you need to be dwelling in seclusion. If
you're like delighting in company say
even if you are actually dwelling in
seclusion but internally you still have
delight towards mere association with
people talking seeing people that will
be an obstacle to see the sign of the
mind which is then the obstacle to
sapati. So those are prerequisites for
the right view. So it's like you got to
make do that all their work just to come
to the point to see your mind
for that mind to become a reference of
you know whether to tighten or loosen
the strings and all those other
similars. So obviously people that met
the Buddha were fortunate for one reason
or the other and he guided their mind
without them even seeing their mind.
Then they saw it. Sure. And when when
they would exclaim, oh, it's like
turning upside what was upside down,
turning it right. What was first place,
second, what second place, first? Like
correcting the what was always there.
But without his guidance, they wouldn't
have been seen. So when the Buddha would
um talk about the the perils
of sensuality and so it's not about like
to shame a person or something. It's
it's nothing to do with that. It's just
the fact that if the mind still relies
upon um
sensuality, the entire domain of
sensuality, the possibility of
sensuality as means of escaping
suffering deep down it never going to uh take on
deep down it never going to uh take on
that suffering because in order to be
really understand to to correctly
understand what the cause of suffering
is, you need to take it on. That's just
not an option to oh, I'll avoid it and
somehow it's going to get resolved by
itself. So for as long as you're giving in to
So for as long as you're giving in to
the ways of avoiding that confinement of
the duka seeing the you know the four
great mountains coming from all
directions as they would say recognizing
the situation the opening amidst that
confinement will never become apparent.
The opening as in the right view the
direction that really takes you out of
the the the whole frees you from the
whole picture. So it's not about like oh
you should um you're a bad person or
something if you're still attracted to
to sense objects and so on. It's it's
it's way
subtler and past any moral judgment.
Moral judgments are on the level of five
precepts basically. But now presumably
if you want to train your mind to the
point that you can actually see it
correctly to the point that you can
develop chitanita which is a
prerequisite for the right view then
it's like okay you got to take these on
these trainings these confinements for
the sake of kind of well yeah preventing
the mind from spilling in the direction
where it shouldn't be spilling towards
and then you get to be left with it the
way it is and with the causes of that
suffering right there and then not
yesterday, not tomorrow, not because of
this, not because of that, but because
of the state of mind affected with cra also that
also that
>> uh if you are attracted to some a
beautiful thing,
>> you're doing it. You are attract there's
a reason for that. There's a reason that
is attractive for you.
And the the reason is you are
>> uncomfortable here. You're suffering
here. You can't face it. You're trying
looking for an escape from suffering. So
you >> well it not necessarily it doesn't need
>> well it not necessarily it doesn't need
to be like that kind of relational in a
sense that whenever you're attracted
because you're suffering right there and
then and you're escaping something
>> like people can genuinely be fine
>> overall but still cultivate the
attraction. So there's nothing currently there
So there's nothing currently there
undermining them in terms of suffering,
in terms of a threat.
>> Yeah. And Yeah.
>> Because the way you said it sounds like
whenever you're attracted is because
something is right there you're trying
to escape from.
>> Yeah. It might be not be an acute
suffering, but in general it's a
it's an escape from the liability to
suffering, you know.
>> Well, yes. Yeah. If there Sure. So it's
like a subtle thing and like well even
even just an escape from discontent.
>> Yeah.
>> Boredom.
>> Yeah. That's what Yeah.
>> Those those things are already this
subtle unpleasantness
>> that if you don't escape from would turn
into full-on pressure and anxiety and
panic attack.
>> So it's like the the the neutrality of
my present experience is just too much
for the mind to handle. It's like ah
>> so it's by chasing something beautiful
>> that is
>> well it's also the the chase as well
>> the chase is
>> see having having that chase having that
movement having that activation pretty
much those
>> that's exactly kind of already offers
see the fact that you could move
already implies that you're not as
confined as you might have felt
>> so that's why fundamentally sankaras
follow immediately after a vija Yeah,
the movement follows immediately after
ignorance and it proliferates that
ignorance.
But uh it's interesting point um
and then so just thinking about the
chase. So chasing
some attractive object
or beautiful object chasing it you know
helps with ignor ignoring of the greater
context perpetuated
>> which uh doesn't change that thing in
the background that you are the reason
for your chase. And then when you get to
that when you get that pleasant thing
that you're chasing whatever it might be
that that background context remains
there. >> Yeah. Nothing has changed really. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Nothing has changed really. Yeah.
>> But now the chase has stopped. So
>> So you got to find a new one
>> and so you're running out of options.
>> You know you have to keep on
diversifying your chases.
>> You're running out of options and also
uh your senses your sense organs are
aging. disintegrating
which means um sights will be harder to
see, sounds will be harder to to enjoy.
Taste won't offer as much of a relief as
before. In other words, you won't be
able to to to be distracted
on account of sense objects because your
senses cannot appreciate them as much as
before. It's just aching, failing, not
as good as it was and so on. And that's
also like an impending thing in the
direction where you're heading.
>> So again, if you are noticing or you
understand that
well I would say if you understand that
a thing is attractive and it's the
beautiful the value in that beautiful
thing is to chase because it covers up
your discontent.
now. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> But if you don't chase that thing and
you understand that you are actually
discontent here and now,
>> that's why you you
>> that's why you'll be going. Yeah.
Exactly. >> And that getting that thing doesn't
>> And that getting that thing doesn't
actually resolve the issue of your
resistance to this discontent here.
>> Well, it does offer a relief though.
>> It offers a relief, but not
>> it's not just like, oh, it's nothing's
real. It's not true.
>> Sensuality offers a factual relief.
Chase offers a factual relief through
distraction. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> It's just that you need to recognize and
convince yourself rightly that those
reliefs are actually making things
worse. They're not truly relieving you.
They're giving you a temporary kind of
cover up but at the expense of making
the whole condition worse. Like
scratching the
>> the itch relieves you. Factually
relieves you. Factually makes you feel
ah now it's better. The itch is gone.
but it's making the whole skin condition
a lot a lot worse. So, it's going to
itch even harder next time. And the time
will come when you won't be able to
scratch basically one way or the other.
>> Yeah.
>> Either because your hands don't work or
because there's no more things to
scratch with.
>> Um
>> so yeah, that that highlights the the
danger >> of the chasing
>> of the chasing
>> and also the escape because like well
that's the this is the perpetuation of
my problem. What highlights the danger
in the escape?
>> Uh knowing that what you just said, you
know that uh
>> and what highlights the knowing of that?
>> What highlights it?
>> Well, what brings it about?
>> Self-reflection that
>> And what brings that about
>> duka? Suffering that
>> Yeah. suffering that you basically
impose by first and foremost saying no
to those things.
>> So you heard about it. You could think
and ponder all you want and analyze and
and and and and psychologize and make
all the connections. If you don't give
it up first,
none of this will have anything to land
on. And that's because sometimes people
would think, well, I know I should give
it up and if I ponder hard enough, it
will be given up for me, so to speak. if
I meditate rightly or if I do this
rightly then I'll just lose interest in
sensuality altogether without having to
just give it up out of faith first
and that will never work. That's why
even when the when the arans wanted
after the Buddha passed away when they
were deciding what to chant first what
to recite first dhamma or the vinea they
says well there is no dhamma without
vina so they they spent I don't know how
long reciting just absolute
technicalities of what you shouldn't do
and if you do that what are the
condition the whole patim moa basically
so it's like even even mindlessly like
as in like I have no any understanding
of the right view the right practice
Doesn't matter.
Sensuality needs to be said no to first.
You need to be restrained first. Then
you can develop the understanding. Sure,
it's you could do both at the same time.
But what you cannot do is not say no to
sensuality as means of existential
escape that we just described and think
that pondering about dhamma will somehow
do it for you. Pondering about dharma
without saying no might make you help
you fortify the reasons for eventually
saying no to it
>> but it's only after you say no to it
that then you can know okay now I am
heading in the right direction
>> even if I'm still not terribly clear
about the nuances of those directions
the fact that the training has been
undertaken means I am heading the right
direction that's why vina means training
monk's rules usually vina basically Ally
means monk's rules what what they should
shouldn't do means training says when
one undertakes the vine means one
undertakes the training of the dharma
>> so because it it reveals that discontent
>> resistance to even if you don't
necessarily see it or understand it at
the time
>> it brings it up there it doesn't cover
it up
>> so eventually you'll have stuff to work
with on the right level because it's it
always has been there just that you've
been [clears throat]
>> like too busy immediately automat
automatically covering it up and just
following the directions of distra
distraction and so on.
And so the the escape
so you don't you say no the the danger
becomes clear the escape becomes clear
>> well eventually
>> yeah things become clearer
>> you say no and then the confinement
becomes clear
>> the confinement yeah and
>> because now you're left with like with
just an intense pressure to just well
yeah run go back to the wilderness.
>> Yeah. So the elephant has been caught
>> for for at least
a certain amount of time. All that is
going to think about is its wilderness
that has been extracted from.
>> So in other words, when you take on the
restraint, training in restraint, yeah,
initially all the mind will think about
is things you said no to. It's going to
feel worse in that sense. But if you
don't open the gates, if you don't lower
the fences, then it will come down
within that. And then you get to see
that the whole urge towards that
wilderness was the reason you were going into the
was the reason you were going into the
wilderness. In other words, if the
arising of sensuality in your mind or
sensual desire, that's the word I was
looking for. If the rising of desire in
your mind
>> was not already in and of itself
unpleasant, you would have never gone to the lens
you would have never gone to the lens
and pursuits of sense objects as you
used to do as you would be doing because
if the arising of desire is neutral well
it ends there and then but the arising
of desire already hurts.
So that's what I mean like restraint
reveals that sensuality is actually
painful but unless you're restrained
whenever sensuality arises with that
pain you project it onto the sense
objects like oh it's it hurts because I
don't have that so then you go for it to
appease the pain but the fact is it
still hurts first.
So the sensuality is factually
unpleasant. Since desire is factually
pleasant, doesn't matter the amount of
pleasure you gain on top of it.
It's always going to be driven by the
pain of the desire. Because if desire
were not painful, well, you wouldn't be
moving with it.
>> Yeah. There would be no activity.
>> Yeah.
>> It wouldn't be a desire. Can you even
conceive any desire that's not slightly
uncomfortable
>> that doesn't carry that thread of
discomfort that you're trying to
basically >> escape run away from
>> escape run away from
>> appease and uh so
so
seeing that and not no longer resisting
the discomfort discomfort
Then
what value has beauty and what
what is the problem with you know you no
longer if you're no longer resisting your
if you're no longer resisting your
discontent your dooka here
>> then
there is no need for a beautiful thing
>> well eventually the whole yeah the whole
beautiful things are seen for what they
are escape from the pain that they
inflicted upon you in the first
So, it's a vicious It's a vicious cycle.
Exactly. Like a like an addiction.
>> The only reason you go back to drugs is
because you've been taking them.
>> Yeah.
>> And that's why you need to go back to
them because you've been taking them.
>> You stop taking them, you won't be going
back to them.
>> Yeah.
>> But
>> time has to pass until the mind calms
down away from it.
And there is no other way to go about
it. How much you're gonna suffer on
account of it depends how how wild your
mind was to begin with. Some people's
minds were not that wild. And when they
uh uh impose the level of that kind of
an infinite notion of I will never go
back to these things. The mind panics a
little bit but it comes down. Some
people it just goes into full-on panic
attack like like too too hard to bear.
But >> you have to go through it you know.
>> you have to go through it you know.
Well, you have to go through it like and
if it's too much again, you do it
gradually. You'll fail. You go back to
it. But at no point should you allow
yourself to develop views that I don't
have to go through it.
Because even if you just just put
everything else aside from the sutas,
just take the sheer amount of
similarities that the Buddha gave about
taming the elephant or the the thread
horse and the cults and stuff and just
just think about the principles of
training a wild animal and you'll see it
always boils down to that. And there is
no way around it.
>> Yeah. [snorts]
>> Like
>> Yeah.
>> The elephant used to the wilderness,
roaming where he wants, doing what he
wants, will
resist, kick and scream, urinate in
default until it comes down when it's being
until it comes down when it's being
trapped. Then when it comes down, that's
okay. Now we can begin to like offer it
food, take it for a walk. In other
words, you could begin to train it. But
trying to train, trying to command and
tell elephant what to do while it's
still allowed to roam in the wilderness.
Well, that's just like talking to a
>> to a rock or something. It makes no
difference. There's no communication
there.
So would you would you say then
um
>> so I think one one thing to add would be
>> like um you know when if a person hears
this it's like yes there's an imperative
you must uh abandon sensuality but it's
not something that you must or you even
can do it overnight like okay from
tomorrow onwards never again and then
I'll be a sautana you [snorts] need to
recognize well you could try from
tomorrow onwards ever again. And then
see what happens tomorrow. See when your
mind gets when that elephant wakes up
and wants to go back to the
>> the what it's used to the pastures and
stuff. See what force comes up, how
forceful it is. Most likely you're going
to fail.
But that's the point to recognize that
it's not about like as I said a moral
commandment. It's about training.
So five precepts, add celibacy, add more
precepts gradually. But it's all about
the training. It's about
preventing that mind from spilling into
these unh wholesome wildernesses and
ways of of of basically existing. They
were covering up they were covering up
the dooka, covering up the source of
duka, covering up the discomfort and
just keeping it dependent on that
constant roaming about emotional. I want
this, I want that, I want this. And if
there is nothing left for me to do or
go, then the panic sets in and anxiety
and comes up and stuff. So it's like you
want to address that before that
actually comes before the elephant is
too old to move and stuff, but the mind
still wants to go and do all of these
things. >> And then now you're just being well like
>> And then now you're just being well like
the the old king in that suta when said
well I'm telling you now because he
asked him like what would you do if I
tell you there's a big army coming from
the east?
>> So well I would go and fight them there
from the west. I'll go and fight them
there. What if I tell you they're like
coming from from all direction? No,
sorry. No, it wasn't the big army. It
was the What if tell a big mountain
coming from this?
>> Yeah. Crushing all things.
>> Crushing all things in its way. Yeah.
And he says, "Well, I would run to the
west." Well, if I tell you there's a man
coming from the west, no. What if I tell
you they're coming from all four
directions. >> So, no direction that you can go or
>> So, no direction that you can go or
engage with will offer you an escape
>> because it's actually heading towards
the destruction.
>> Yeah. And then he says well in that case
I would give up the lay life and
practice the dharma while because the
time is short. [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> So it's like so that that recognition
that that that principle that framework
that there is no as I said there's no
changing that like you can recognize
your current limitations and then start
working on your environment. They would
then support
you training in the precepts more. they
would then obviously calm down the mind
gradually more and more and more. Um so
don't expect like to just just magically
resolve because you have such a strong
determination and take it over like next
day take take on all the precepts and
sense restraint and then the mind will
just magically follow. No, it's going to
be ups and downs but the most important
thing is that your view and the value of
doing it doesn't change. You don't
halfway through convince yourself no I
don't actually have to keep the brief.
No, I don't actually have to. No, you
don't need to give these things up
>> because deep down you know that you do.
>> It's just you you don't want to believe
it because it's too uncomfortable and
you don't want training to be about
going through that discomfort. You want
it to be about something else but that's
just now becomes delusional basically.
So as I was saying like in the beginning
that uh the fact that you are attracted
uh the fact that you are attracted
>> you understand all these things to some
degree. The fact that you are attracted
reveals that there is a problem
>> but the mind is still there is some
resistance right here to something.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And so
at at that kind of stage so to speak or
whatever attraction
attraction
reveals the issue for it's like it's
like a kind of revealing issue. It
>> well saying no to attraction would
reveal >> saying no to attraction. I'm not
>> saying no to attraction. I'm not
>> because if you're still going with it
>> I know I'm attracted but I'm not going
towards it.
>> Yeah
>> because if I go towards it of course.
Yeah. Then I'm ignoring the the I'm
trying I'm covering things up.
>> Yeah. Uh but knowing attraction is there
and not saying no to it. It's highlights
the fact why it's there. [clears throat]
>> Why why it has such a pull because
there's a push
>> here
>> away from
just boredom, neutrality or pain or
whatever. >> Confinement.
>> Confinement.
>> Yeah. Confinement.
>> Duka
>> which is da already the form of duka.
Yeah. And that as that suta one suta says that
And that as that suta one suta says that
if you stop delighting in you get rid of
delight that craving
>> then beautiful things in the world just
remain as they are.
>> Yeah.
>> So
>> things haven't changed but you just
completely overcome your desire towards
them because you stop running out from
confinement that that piga of your own
existence you stop running away from it and you
you stop running away from it and you
stop running away from it. the purpose
for depending on all these beautiful
things and using them for distraction
that's completely evaporates.
>> Yeah.
>> Conceivable. Yeah.
>> Like the reasons for engaging with
sensuality are gone now. Yeah.
>> So there's no need for movement
>> of the sensual kind of the through the
desire.